(Kurokawa Household)
[黑川宅]
As Mr. Kurokawa was typing away, drinking wine as he did,
黑川先生一边喝酒—边打字的时候
he was hit over the head from behind.
被人从背后重击头部而死
The murder weapon should be the statue next to him.
凶器大概就是死者身旁的这个铜像
There's still one thing we are not clear of.
但是有一点我们还不太清楚
This seems to be the dying message left by the victim.
这似乎是被害人留下的死亡讯息
However, what does "JUN" refer to?
但“JUN”指的是什么呢
That must indicate the murderer's identity.
那一定是在指凶手
What did you say?
你说什么
Also, the murderer is one of the three of them in this very room!
而且凶手就在那3个人之中
Ooh, Mr. Mouri did a great job this time!
这次叔叔好厉害啊
His wife, Mrs. Mina Kurokawa,
夫人黑川三奈女士
his eldest son, Mr. Daisuke Kurokawa
长子黑川大介先生
and the housemaid, Miss. Manami Nakazawa.
以及女佣中泽真那美小姐这3个人之中
Brilliant, Mouri.
太好了 毛利老弟
So who's the murderer?
那凶手到底是谁呢
The one who killed Mr. Kurokawa is you,
杀害黑川大造先生的真凶就是你
M-Mrs. Kurokawa!
黑 黑川太太
The three letters "JUN" which Kurokawa left behind
黑川先生留下的“JUN”这3个字母
are the first three letters of the month "JUNE".
是英文中六月“JUNE”的缩写
Because June is a dry month,
因为六月常常缺水
people call it "No-water month", or "Minazuki",
又被称为水无月（MINAZUKI）
which refers to Mina!
所以指的就是三奈（MINA）女士
Also, you...
而且你…
So what if I was born in June, it doesn't mean anything!
就算我是六月出生的那又怎么样
What makes you say that this "Minazuki" means "Mina"?
凭什么说水无月就是指三奈啊
Are you going to try to pin this on me with this absurd theory?
你想用这种无聊的笑话来证明我是凶手吗
No, this is just the deduction I made based on logic.
没有 这只是根据逻辑作出的推理
Why would a dying person do something like that?
一个快死了的人还会做这种麻烦事情吗
If it was me, I'd type the murderer's name outright.
要是我的话会直接写下凶手的名字
Inspector Megure, how could you team up against me too?
怎么连警官也这么说啊
Mr. Mouri is at his limit now.
大叔的推理能力也只有这种程度了
It's my turn.
没办法
Is framing an innocent person the job of a detective?
诬陷无辜的人难道就是侦探的工作吗
As usual I'll just use this stun-gun wrist-watch
老方法 用这支手表型麻醉枪
- to put Mr. Mouri to sleep. - If you keep spouting such nonsense, I'll sue you for libel!
让叔叔暂时睡一觉吧 你如果再胡说八道我就告你损害名誉
Ouch, not this again!
好痛 又来了
Here it is, I was waiting for this moment!
开始了 就等这一刻呢
That's right.
没错
I was only joking when I named Mrs. Kurokawa the murderer.
说凶手是黑川太太只是开个玩笑
Joking?
玩笑
Inspector Megure,
目暮警官
please take a closer look at the body.
请仔细观察一下尸体
Only the little finger of Mr. Kurokawa's right hand
黑川先生沾着血迹的手指
was stained with blood.
只有右手的小指而已
Indeed.
确实如此
And which keys have bloodstains on their surface?
那么有哪些按键沾了血迹呢
KE MU and RO, as well as the Caps Lock key.
KE MU RO 还有左边的英文大写切换键
The keys KE MU and RO were stained with blood when Kurokawa
KE MU RO上面的血迹是黑川先生用右手食指
used the index finger of his right hand to press the three letters "JUN".
按下“JUN”这3个键时被小指上的血迹沾到的
But it's impossible for him to use the little finger of his right hand to press on the key on the left.
但应该不会有人用右手小指去按左边的键吧
So, why there are bloodstains on the key on the left side of the keyboard?
那么键盘左边的按键上为什么会沾到血迹呢
I think it's because when Mr. Kurokawa was hit over the head by the murderer
大概是黑川先生被从背后接近的凶手击中后脑时
he touched the back of his head with his right hand.
用右手按住自己的后脑
That was when he got blood on his little finger.
此时右手小指上沾到了血
And when he turned around, he was hit again.
而当他回过头去时又再度受击
As he fell, he hit the keyboard with his little finger and it fell to the floor.
在他倒下时键盘刚好被小指挂到而掉下来
Which means,
也就是说
Mr. Kurokawa didn't press on the Caps Lock key on purpose
键盘左边的英文大写切换键
but in fact only accidentally touched it
并非黑川先生在案发时有意按下的
when he fell.
而是在他倒下时不小心碰到的结果
Mr. Kurokawa waited for the murderer to leave
接着黑川先生等凶手离开后
and then while he still held onto consciousness,
在意识渐渐恍惚之际
he used the last of his strength to spell out the killer's name on the keyboard.
用尽全身最后的力量按下了眼前的键盘
But he wanted to use hiragana to do so!
他想按的其实是平假名
So, the hiragana you get for typing "J-U-N" without the Caps Lock on is
那黑川先生按下的“JUN”代表的假名是
Ma
真（MA）
Na
那（NA）
Mi
美（MI）
Yes.
对
The murderer is the housemaid, Manami Nakazawa.
凶手就是女佣中泽真那美小姐
It's you.
就是你
You must be joking again, Mr. Detective.
你是在开玩笑吧 侦探先生
You don't have any proof.
你又没有证据
Of course I have.
证据我当然有
You must have taken off your slippers when you committed the crime.
你在行凶时一定把拖鞋脱掉了吧
Because if you wore slippers,
穿着拖鞋在地板上走的话
you wouldn't be able to approach Mr. Kurokawa quietly from behind.
就没法悄悄地从背后接近黑川先生了
But you didn't notice that
可是你没有注意到
you had stepped on the blood on the floor.
你踩到了溅在地板上的血
The unnatural shape of the bloodstain at Exhibit A proves that.
A点血迹那不自然的形状就能证明这点
The bottom of your white sock
你的白袜子底下
must be stained with blood.
一定沾有血迹
When you gave your statements to the police,
警方对你做笔录时
you said you never got close to the body, right?
你说从没有接近过尸体对吧
Can we check your sock now?
可以让我们检验一下袜子上的血迹吗
Kurokawa killed my husband one year ago.
黑川在1年前杀死了我的丈夫
So you are the wife of the patient whom my father performed heart surgery on...
这么说你就是我爸做心脏手术那个病人的…
That's right.
没错
The patient who died after surgery performed by Kurokawa while he was drunk was my husband.
我就是那个黑川酒醉后动手术害死的病人的妻子
No one in this family recognized me after I changed my haircut and my name.
只不过改了发型和名字居然就没人认出我
So it seems that that such incidents mean nothing to you guys.
看来那件事对你们来说是微不足道的吧
In order to sue Kurokawa,
我为了起诉黑川
I asked his colleagues to testify,
曾请求医院的相关人士提供证词
but no one was willing to help.
但是却没有人愿意帮忙
Because they were all afraid of Kurokawa.
因为他们都害怕黑川
So you killed him in order to avenge your husband.
这么说你是替你丈夫报仇
Today is the first anniversary of my husband's death.
今天是我丈夫的祭日
I don't regret a thing, not one bit.
我一点都不觉得后悔
Because I have already avenged him.
因为我已经替他报仇雪恨了
Let's go.
走吧
It seems that I helped Mr. Mouri make a great contribution again.
看来这次我又帮叔叔立了大功
Detective Conan The Time-Bombed Skyscraper
名侦探柯南 计时引爆摩天楼
I am Shinichi Kudo, a high school detective.
我是高中生侦探工藤新一
When I was at the theme park with my childhood friend Ran Mouri,
在和青梅竹马的同学毛利兰去游乐园玩时
I witnessed an exchange inside a secret criminal syndicate.
目击了黑衣人进行可疑交易的现场
At that time, I, eyes fixed only on the deal in process,
当时只顾着偷看交易情况的我
didn't notice that one member of their gang had snuck up behind me.
没注意到他的同伙从背后靠近
I was forced to take a kind of poison by that man.
我被那个男人强行灌下毒药
When I woke up,
等我醒来时
I found my body had shrunk to that of a child.
发现身体竟然变小了
If they found out that Shinichi Kudo is still alive,
如果被他们知道工藤新一还活着
they would try to kill me
不但我的性命难保
or even hurt my families and friends.
还会危及到我身边的人
So I listened to Professor Agasa's advice
在阿笠博士的建议下
and hid my true identity.
我隐瞒了真实身份
When Ran asked about my name,
当小兰问到我的名字时
the name Conan Edogawa suddenly came to me.
情急之下我化名为江户川柯南
In order to get more information about that Black Organization,
为了得到那些家伙的情报
I moved into Ran's house, since her father is a detective.
我住进了父亲是侦探的小兰家
However, Mr. Mouri isn't really much of a detective.
但是这位叔叔却是个糊涂侦探
I can't watch his bungling deductions anymore, so I pretend to be him
看不下去的我便装成了叔叔
and solve a lot of tricky cases using my natural deduction genius.
利用我天生的推理能力解决了许多疑难案件
With my help, Mr. Mouri has become more and more famous as a detective.
叔叔也拜我所赐成了名气越来越响的名侦探
And I
而我现在
have become a primary school student.
却变回了一个小学生
What's more, I was obliged to join the Junior Detective Squad,
还被迫跟同班同学步美 元太 光彦
made up of Ayumi, Genta and Mitsuhiko who are all my classmates.
组成了少年侦探团
Next, please let me introduce the tools which Agasa invented for me.
接着就向大家介绍博士为我发明的道具
First, it's the stun-gun wrist-watch.
首先是手表型麻醉枪
After I aim at the target, I press on the button to shoot a tranquilizer dart
通过瞄准器对准目标按下按钮就能发射麻醉针
which can put people to sleep instantly.
可以在瞬间让人昏睡
Next is this voice-changing bowtie.
接着是蝴蝶结变声器
By turning the dial on the back,
只要转动后面的旋钮
I am able to imitate all kinds of voices that I've heard.
不管是大人还是小孩任何人的声音都可以模仿
Next is my killer stuff, power-enhancing kicking shoes.
接下来的必杀道具是脚力增强鞋
These shoes use electricity and magnetic fields to stimulate my feet muscles,
利用电流和磁力刺激脚部的穴位
allowing me to kick objects with tremendous power.
把肌肉的力量发挥到极限
If I want to chase after a criminal, I'll need this turbo-engine skateboard.
追踪犯人的话则要用这个双涡轮引擎滑板
However, it will not work without solar power,
不过因为动力来自太阳能
which is its only weakness.
只能在有太阳时使用是它唯一的缺点
That's right, I almost forgot.
对了 我差点忘记了
My Detective Boys Badge has a tiny walkie talkie inside
少年侦探团的徽章内藏有超小型无线电对讲机
which can also emit a signal. It's simply perfect.
还兼有信号发射器功能 简直无懈可击
I have a lot more tools too,
除此之外还有很多道具
but my most powerful weapon is this.
不过最厉害的武器却是这个
My body may have shrunk, but my mind is still as sharp as ever.
身体变小了头脑却依然灵活
I am the famous detective who can solve any case.
无所不知的名侦探
Only one truth will prevail!!
真相永远只有一个
(Professor Hiroshi's House April 26th Saturday)
[阿笠博士家 4月26日星期六]
For the attention of Mr. Kudo.
给工藤优作先生
To Mr. Kudo.
工藤优作先生启
They were all sent to my father.
全部都是老爸的信
Maybe the letters are all from fans of detective fiction.
大概都是侦探迷寄来的吧
I heard that the Night Baron series your father wrote a while ago
你爸爸不久前写的暗夜男爵系列的新作
made the bestseller list in America.
听说在美国登上了畅销书排行榜呢
That's right.
对啊
But he's in Switzerland now.
可是他现在人在瑞士
It's really difficult to forward these fan letters to him,
经常满世界乱跑
since he's always traveling around the world.
要把侦探迷的信寄给他还真是麻烦啊
Doesn't he give you the freedom to do as you like?
他不是放手让你去做自己喜欢的事吗
It's only fair you at least do something for him.
帮他做点事也是应该的吧
I know.
我知道啦
By the way, professor,
对了 博士
what are you making now?
你在做什么东西
Is it a new tool for me?
是给我的新道具吗
Sorry, it's not that kind of thing.
很遗憾 并不是那种小玩意
Humans created airplanes after they studied how birds could fly in the sky,
人类研究了翱翔天空的鸟类才制造出飞机
but no one has created anything using the mechanics of how insects flap their wings.
但是却还没有人完成昆虫振翅的机械原理
If I could be the first to apply those mechanics to toy manufacturing,
如果我能最早将其完成并做成玩具贩卖的话
then children all over the world would be captivated.
届时一定会引起世界各地儿童的强烈兴趣
Then, I'll be sure to earn a lot of money, even become a billionaire!
这样我就会赚进大把钞票成为亿万富翁
When do you think you'll ever achieve that dream?
你那个梦几时才能实现啊
I've been listening to the same thing since I was a child.
从小听到大 都已经听烦了
Anyway,
不过话说回来
none of the letters were addressed to me.
这里面竟没有一封是写给我的
Perhaps the world already forgot about me.
我大概已经被这个世界遗忘了
One for me!
是给我的
Teiji Moriya?
森谷帝二
That Teiji Moriya?
是那个森谷帝二吗
Sorry to have written this letter to you all of a sudden.
非常冒昧突然写这封信给您
I've learned about the cases you solved
您这位高中生侦探的活跃表现
from the newspaper and on the television.
我早就从报纸和电视上了解到了
I've been hoping to talk to you in person.
一直希望能有机会与您见面聊聊
At half past three on the afternoon of Tuesday, April 29th,
我将在4月29日星期二下午3点半
I'll have a tea party in my garden.
于寒舍举办午后花园茶会
I hope you could come by at that time.
希望您届时能莅临指教
What is it? An invitation to a party?
怎么了 是宴会的邀请函吗
Professor,
博士
you know who Teiji Moriya is, right?
你知道森谷帝二这个人吧
Of course I do.
我当然知道了
He's the professor in charge of the architecture department at Kyoto University.
他是东都大学建筑系的教授
And also one of the best architects in Japan.
也是日本首屈一指的建筑师
Why does such a famous architect want to talk to me?
这么有名的建筑师怎么会邀请我呢
Architects are also considered artists.
建筑师也可以算是一种艺术家
Maybe he's looking for new inspiration.
或许他需要一点新的刺激吧
Not to mention that Professor Moriya and I are both geniuses.
更何况森谷教授和我都是天才型的人啊
Geniuses?
天才型吗
A garden party?
花园茶会
Yes.
是啊
I happen to be dealing with a case right now and can't go.
我现在手上正好有案子没法去参加
You want me to go to the party in your stead?
你要我替你去
It says on the invitation that I could bring someone with me.
邀请函上写着欢迎携伴前往
Ran, you can go with your father and the boy who lives in your house...
小兰可以跟你爸爸还有寄住在你家的那个…
What's his name again?
叫什么来着
Conan.
柯南啊
That's right. The three of you should go together.
对了 你们3人一起去吧
I've already put the invitation in your mailbox.
邀请函我已经放到小兰你家的信箱里了
You finally called me and that was all you have to say?
难得你打电话给我没想到竟然是这种事
Fine, I'll do it – but on one condition.
可以 不过我有个条件
One condition?
条件
You have to go to see a midnight movie with me next Saturday.
下个星期六陪我一起去看午夜场电影
What's that got to do with anything?
有什么关系嘛
We haven't seen each other for so long.
我们好久没见面了
I'll meet you at 10 p.m. in front of the hall of Beika City Building.
晚上10点在米花都市大楼的大厅碰面
Wait, wait a minute.
等 等一下啦
I can't be there next Saturday.
下个星期六我不方便
Can we make it another day-
可不可以以后再…
No.
不行
It has to be May 3rd.
一定要在5月3日那天
Shinichi, do you prefer red or blue?
新一你喜欢红色还是蓝色
Red or blue?
红色和蓝色
Why did you suddenly ask that?
干嘛突然问这个
It's nothing, just answer the question.
你别管啦 快点回答
Then red.
那就红色吧
Red?
红色
Is that so? As I expected.
是吗 果然是红色啊
I knew you would pick red.
我就知道你会选红色
Because red is your favorite color!
因为红色是你喜欢的颜色
Is dinner still not ready?
晚饭还没好吗
Fine, I'll go prepare it.
好啦 我现在就去准备
That's all, Shinichi.
就这样了 新一
At 10 p.m. on 3rd. Don't forget.
3号晚上10点 你不要忘了哦
Jeez.
真是的
If I could just casually go to a movie with you,
要是我能跟你去看电影的话
I wouldn't ask you to attend a garden party for me.
就不用拜托你替我去参加茶会了
Speaking of which,
不过话说回来
why does it have to be May 3rd?
为什么一定要在5月3日呢
Is there anything special about May 3rd?
难道5月3日有什么事吗
May 4th is the day when
之后的5月4日
Holmes and Professor Moriarty both fell down the Reichenbach Falls.
是福尔摩斯和莫里亚蒂教授坠入莱辛巴赫瀑布之日
Next, on May 5th, it's National Boys' Day.
接下来的5月5日是男孩节
Conan.
柯南
Are you going back home now?
你现在要回家吗
Inspector, you got another case again?
警官先生 又有什么案子了吗
Yes, we do have some more cases.
是有些案子
Let me introduce you two,
我来介绍一下
this is Officer Shiratori, who just transferred to our department.
这是最近调到我们课的白鸟警官
I am Shiratori.
我是白鸟
Inspector Megure told me a lot about you.
警官跟我说过很多你的事情
I heard you always noticed those things that others had ignored.
听说你每次都会注意到别人忽略的地方
That's just by coincidence.
没有啦 那都是碰巧而已
I guessed so too.
我想也是
Coincidences happen all the time.
这种碰巧的事常常会发生
You are very blunt.
你说话还真不客气
We have so many cases lately.
最近案子太多
I guess I won't be able to enjoy my golden week vacation this year.
今年的黄金假期大概也不能好好过了
See you.
再见
Golden week?
黄金假期
That's right.
对了
May 3rd is Constitution Memorial Day.
5月3日是宪法纪念日
So what?
那又怎么样
Birthday?
生日
That's right.
对啊
May 4th is Shinichi's birthday,
因为5月4日是新一的生日
so I asked him to see a movie with me on May 3rd.
所以我就约他5月3日去看午夜场电影
At midnight, I'll give him the red shirt I bought for him.
在12点的时候把我买的红色休闲衫送给他
It's a surprise for him.
打算给他一个惊喜
That's right. My birthday is on May 4th.
对哦 5月4日是我的生日啊
I can't believe I forgot that.
我竟然把这件事给忘了
Then which movie are you two going to see?
那你们要去看什么电影啊
The Legend of the Red Line.
红线的传说
Red... red line?
红 红线
Don't you know that legend?
你们不知道吗
When a boy and the girl who are destined to be together are born,
命中注定会在一起的男女出生时
there is a red line which ties their little fingers together?
两人的小指上会绑着一条红线的传说
It's a romantic movie about this legend.
是以这个传说为主题的浪漫爱情电影
It's a click flick.
是少女电影啊
Check this,
你们看这个
Shinichi and I have the same lucky color in May, which is red.
我和新一五月份的幸运色都是红色
That's why I decided to see that movie.
所以我才决定要去看这部片子的
Even if you decided, it's no use.
你决定了也没用啊
There's no way we can see that movie together.
我们根本不可能—起去看电影嘛
Wait.
先等一下
Did you just say you would watch a midnight screening?
你刚才说要去看午夜场是吗
Yes.
对啊
No, no.
不行 不行
I'll never allow it.
我绝对不允许
Young couples just make out for the whole night in the cinema.
年轻男女在昏暗的电影院里整晚地亲热像什么话
It's not what you think!
才不是那样呢
Don't talk nonsense!
你别乱说好吗
Shinichi always forgets about his birthday,
谁叫新一每年都会把自己的生日忘了嘛
so I have to remind him every year.
所以我每年都要提醒他
Otherwise he would grow another year older without even knowing it.
不然他就白白地长大了一岁啊
Actually, I just became younger.
不过我现在反而变小了
Even so,
但是这个
you two are just high school students.
你们都还是高中生啊
By the way,
对了
dad, let's go to Teiji Moriya's garden party together.
爸爸 我们一起去参加森谷帝二的花园茶会吧
Why-why are you suddenly bringing that up?
你 你怎么突然说这个
Shinishi was invited to the party, but he couldn't go.
受邀请的本来是新一 可他没办法去
Conan, let's go together.
柯南也一起去吧
Okay.
我去我去
How could I go there with an invitation sent to Shinichi?
我怎么可能拿新一那小子的邀请函去
Isn't Teiji Moriy that famous architect?
森谷帝二就是那个有名的建筑师吗
This is a historic meeting between the famous detective and famous architect.
这可是名侦探跟名建筑师的历史性会面哦
The famous detective and the famous architect.
名侦探跟名建筑师啊
He's so easy to fool.
他这个人真是好骗
(Moriya's House April 29th Tuesday)
[森谷宅 4月29日星期二]
Conan, wait.
柯南 不行啦
You need an invitation to get in.
要有邀请函才能进去
Please come in.
请进
Thanks.
谢谢
It's so grand!
好壮观哦
This is the 17th century architectural style popular during the British Stuart period.
不愧是17世纪英国斯图亚特王朝时代的建筑风格
Dad, I never know you know so much about architecture.
爸爸对建筑这么了解啊
People used to call your dad the walking library.
以前别人都称你老爸活图书馆呢
Now look to the left and right carefully.
你现在再仔细看看左右两边
If we stand in the middle, we'll find the views on the left and right identical,
站在正中间左右的景观完全一样呢
both the garden and the buildings.
花园和建筑都是
This is the so-called symmetrical structure.
这种建筑就是所谓的左右对称式设计
Professor Moriya spent his childhood in Britain up until high school.
森谷教授一直到高中都是在英国度过的
Therefore, he is fond of buildings in the British style...
因此他非常喜欢英国式的建筑特别是…
In particular...
特别是…
He has an obsession with classical style constructions.
对古典式建筑风格有着格外的执着
So he brought a cheat sheet.
原来还带着小抄
His name was "Joji" before,
他的名字原本叫“贞治”
but he changed to Teiji because the latter's hiragana is symmetrical.
后来还因此改成了左右对称的“帝二”呢
That's just going too far.
简直是病态
This is the first time I saw such a beautiful garden.
不过我是第一次看到这么漂亮的花园呢
I'm honored to receive your compliment.
能够得到你的称赞是我的荣幸
Nice to meet you, I'm Teiji Moriya.
初次见面 我是森谷帝二
I-I'm Ran Mouri.
我 我叫毛利兰
This is my father and Conan Edogawa.
这是家父和江户川柯南
Today, Shinichi, no,
今天因为新一 不
Kudo couldn't come,
因为工藤无法前来
so we are here in his stead.
我们是代替他来的
Really?
是这样
So Kudo couldn't be here.
工藤不能来啊
But uncle is also a famous detective.
不过这个叔叔也是个名侦探哦
What do you mean by "also"?
小鬼 “也是”是什么意思啊
I am Kogoro Mouri.
在下是毛利小五郎
You are the famous...
你就是那位大名鼎鼎的…
It's an honor to meet you.
请多指教
This way please.
这边请
The tea party will be held in the back garden.
茶会就在后花园举行
The back garden is beautiful too.
后花园也是一样漂亮
Huh, a tea party held by a famous architect really is something.
不愧是名建筑师办的茶会
The guests are all musicians, models,
不是音乐家和模特
entrepreneurs, critics,
就是大企业家和评论家
and famous actors
要不然就是名演员
who are always on television.
全都是在电视上常见的熟面孔
Please make yourself at home
来 不要客气
and enjoy your afternoon.
请好好地享受这午后的时光吧
So pretty.
真漂亮
Are they all hand-made?
这全是手工制作的吗
But of course.
那当然了
This is a formal tea party, so it's only natural to treat my guests with hand-made snacks.
正式的茶会当然要用手制点心招待客人
Please, help yourself.
请用吧
I'll take a bite then.
那我就不客气了
How does it taste?
味道如何呢
This biscuit tastes incredible.
这个饼干好好吃哦
I'm glad you like it.
你喜欢就好
All that time I spent paid off in the end, then.
我昨晚所花的工夫总算是值得了
Sir, I didn't know you were good at baking too.
大师 原来您还擅长厨艺啊
I have to be, since I live alone.
没办法啊 我可是孤家寡人一个
All the snacks here,
今天摆在这里的所有点心
the scones, sandwiches and biscuits were all made by myself.
烤饼 三明治还有饼干都是我亲手做的
I'm the kind of person who only trusts myself with such things.
我的性格就是只有自己亲手做才放心
I see.
原来如此
These beautiful buildings must have come into the world because of this spirit.
那些美丽的建筑就是因为有这种精神才诞生的吧
I can't call something without a sense of beauty "architecture"..
没有美感的东西我可不承认那是建筑
A lot of young architects today
现在有不少年轻的建筑师
have no acknowledgement of beauty.
根本缺乏对美的意识
They have to be more responsible to their works.
他们必须对自己的作品更有责任感才行
By the way, Mr. Mouri,
对了 毛利先生
do you mind if I give you a riddle?
请教你一个谜题不介意吧
A riddle?
谜题吗
Yes.
是的
Try to guess the computer passcode of a company operated by three people.
这是猜3个人合伙经营的公司的计算机密码
The famous detective, Kogoro Mouri, should be able to solve it right away.
名侦探毛利小五郎的话应该能马上解开吧
So he is the famous Kogoro Mouri.
他就是有名的毛利小五郎啊
Of course.
当然
Please tell us.
请说吧
Are you sure?
没问题吗
Here is some information regarding the three people.
那么这是那3个人的资料
The passcode is a word which is related to the three of them,
密码是与3个人都有关的词语
and is comprised of a total of five hiragana.
由5个平假名组成
Miss Ran, you should try it too.
小兰小姐你也来试试看吧
The time limit is 3 minutes.
时间限制是3分钟
Everyone, please think about it together.
在场的各位也一起来想想看吧
Then,
那么
your time starts now.
计时开始
There's no shared characters in their names.
他们的名字里没有相同的字
And their birthdates and blood types are different too.
出生日期和血型也都不一样
They even have different hobbies.
爱好也大相径庭
This is much more difficult than I thought.
比我想象的要难得多啊
What is it?
到底是什么
Do they have anything in common?
他们有什么相同点吗
I might have to give up.
我是只能投降了
Let's wait for the expert to give us the answer.
还是等专家来解答吧
Me too.
我也一样
Is dad going to work it out?
爸爸到底行不行啊
Wait.
等等
Their birth years are one year from each other.
3个人的出生年份分别相差1年
I see.
我知道了
It's Momotaro!
桃太郎
Mo-Momotaro?
桃 桃太郎
It's their zodiac signs, Mr. Mouri.
3个人的生肖啊 叔叔
They were born in the years of the monkey, rooster, and dog
他们分别是申 酉 戌年出生
which matches with the monkey, pheasant, and dog
也就是猴 鸡 狗
companions from the legend of Momotaro.
这些都是桃太郎的跟班嘛
Correct, little boy.
完全正确 小弟弟
You are a brilliant one.
你真是太棒了
Sometimes I have to let Mr. Mouri embarrass himself.
偶尔也该让叔叔出个丑才行呢
As a prize for giving the correct answer,
作为猜出正确答案的奖励
I'll give you a tour of my gallery.
我就请柯南你参观我的展览室吧
Ran, you can come too.
小兰小姐也请一起来
Okay.
好
Now, feel free to peruse the exhibition.
来 你们随便参观吧
Ran, we saw this building last time!
小兰姐姐 这不是上次那个吗
That's right.
是啊
This is Mr. Kurokawa's house.
这是黑川先生的房子嘛
Speaking of which, I heard Mr. Kurokawa was murdered.
对了 听说黑川先生被杀害了
I designed that house not long after I became an independent architect.
那栋房子是我刚出道不久时设计的作品
The few works after that one were all designed when I was around thirty.
之后的几个作品也都是我30多岁时设计的
The structures I designed when I was young are not mature enough.
年轻的时候毕竟不够成熟
Please don't look at those too long.
还是请你们别看了
He even designed bridges before.
他连桥梁都设计过啊
By the way, Ran, do you know Kudo well?
对了 小兰小姐你和工藤很熟吗
That's right. We grew up together
是啊 我们俩从小一起长大
and went to the same high school.
也是高中同学
But we haven't seen each other for a long while.
但现在已经很久没见面了
But Shinichi's, that is, his birthday will be on this Sunday.
不过这个星期天是新一的 不 是他的生日
So we are going to watch the movie together.
所以我跟他约好一起去看电影
You must be looking forward to it.
那真是令人期待
I guess you must have bought the gift already.
你一定把礼物也买好了吧
No, I want to buy it on Saturday.
没有 我想星期六再买
Because he likes red, same as me,
因为他和我一样很喜欢红色
and because our lucky color in May is red too,
而且我们五月份的幸运色也都是红色
I'm planning to buy him a red shirt.
所以我打算买一件红色的休闲衫送给他
That sounds like a great gift.
这礼物的确很不错
I think Kudo will be very happy.
我想工藤他一定会很高兴的
Yes.
是的
Crap.
糟糕
I completely forgot the whole birthday thing.
我把生日那天的事完全忘记了
Isn't that Beika City Building?
那不就是米花都市大楼吗
Yes.
是的
We are going to Beika No.1 Cinema to watch the movie.
我们就是要到那里的米花1号电影城看电影
We'll meet at around 10 p.m. in the hall.
我跟他约好晚上10点在大厅碰面
I see.
是这样啊
That building is one of my finest works.
那栋大楼可是我的得意之作
It's the perfect place for
年轻的情侣要庆祝生日的话
young couples to celebrate birthdays.
没有比那里更合适的地方了
What should I do?
到底该怎么办才好
(May 3rd Saturday)
[5月3日星期六]
You can order takeout for dinner.
那晚饭你们就自己叫外卖吧
It's still 10 hours away from 10 p.m.
距离晚上10点还有10个小时
This is nerve-wracking.
真是伤脑筋
I'm leaving.
我走了
Why did I hide?
我为什么要躲啊
Why didn't you turn her down earlier?
那你为什么不早点拒绝她呢
I can't.
我也没办法啊
Whenever I saw Ran's happy face as she counted the days,
只要见到小兰每天数日历时高兴的表情
I couldn't bring myself to reject her.
就没有办法拒绝她了
Professor,
博士
can you make a Shinichi robot for me?
帮我做个新一的分身机器人好不好
That I can't help you with.
这个我可没办法
Even a genius can't do that.
就算我是天才也做不出来
All right.
也是啊
A large quantity of HMX explosives in Toyo Powder Magazine were stolen the day before yesterday.
（前天东洋火药库大量HMX炸药被盗的事件）
Hundreds of police officers were sent out for the search operation.
（目前警方虽已出动上百名警员进行搜查）
But the suspect has yet to be found.
（但尚未查到嫌犯的线索）
This is something serious.
这件事非同小可哦
Yes.
是啊
- Last night, a fire broke out at Mr. Kurokawa's house in Haidochyou, - If someone mixes HMX with plastics,
（昨夜杯户町1户姓黑川的民宅发生火灾） 将HMX和塑胶混合在一起的话
- they'd be able to make plastic explosives.
就能制造出塑胶炸弹了
Last night, a fire broke out at Mr. Kurokawa's house in Haidochyou,
（昨夜杯户町1户姓黑川的民宅发生火灾）
affecting lot of the houses in that neighborhood.
（附近的多家民宅都惨遭波及）
This is Mr. Kurokawa's house, where we went last time.
这栋房子就是上次的黑川宅啊
That's right. The house where the murder took place.
对啊 就是发生命案的那家
Anyway, arson is so common lately.
不过这段时间纵火案还真多啊
the police deducted that they might be dealing with a serial arsonist.
（警方推测很有可能是连续纵火犯）
Hello,
喂 你好
is Kudo there?
请问工藤新一在吗
Please wait a minute.
请稍等
Shinichi, it's for you.
新一 找你的
How did he know that I was here?
他怎么会知道我在这里
What are you talking about?
你在说什么啊
Didn't we transfer all the calls to your family
我们不是把所有打到你家去的电话
to this place?
全都转接到这里来了吗
That's right.
对哦
Sorry.
对不起
Recently I seldom got calls asking for me,
因为最近很少接到找我的电话
so I completely forgot that.
所以都忘记了
This person seems to be using a voice changing device too,
对方说话时好像也用了变声器
he sounds weird.
声音蛮奇怪的
Hello.
喂
Shinichi Kudo?
工藤新一吗
Yes.
是的
Did you watch the news?
你看到新闻报道了吗
I'm the one who stole the explosives from Toyo Powder Magazine.
从东洋火药库把炸药偷走的人就是我
What?
什么
Tell me your cellphone number.
把你的手机号码告诉我吧
I don't feel th need to give my number to someone like you.
我可没有义务把号码告诉你这种人
So, you want to cut off the only way to contact me?
这么说你是想断掉唯一可以和我联络的方法吗
Fine, my number is...
好吧 号码是
Great.
很好
Now, I want you to go to Teimu Tsugawa Greenland Park with your phone.
你现在立刻带着手机到堤向津川绿地公园来
I'll show you something interesting.
我让你看一样有意思的东西
The Greenland Park.
绿地公园
Hurry up, or those kids will die.
不快去的话那些小孩就要死了
What?!
什么
Shinichi-
新一
I have to go there.
总之我先去看看
Could it be a prank?
会不会是有人恶作剧
He even used a voice-changing device, there's definitely something afoot here.
连变声器都用上了肯定有问题
Professor, please call Inspector Megure for me now.
博士 你立刻帮我联络目暮警官
Okay, be careful.
知道了 你要小心一点
I will.
我知道
(Teimu Tsugawa Greenland Park)
[堤向津川绿地公园]
Mitsuhiko, it's my turn now.
光彦 该轮到我了吧
I'd like to play too.
我也想玩玩看
Just wait a few more minutes.
再等一下吧
This is very hard.
这个是很难的哦
It's not easy to control a drone.
遥控飞机可不好操纵
Mitsuhiko.
光彦
What's with that drone?
你那架遥控飞机是怎么回事
Conan.
柯南
A man with a bear gave it to me.
是一个留胡子的人给我的
He also said that this was a bomber.
他还说这是一架轰炸机呢
A bomber?
轰炸机
Is that a bomb,
飞机机身下面绑着的
tied to that drone?
难道是炸弹
Mitsuhiko, give it to me.
光彦 给我
Come on, I'll be the next.
干嘛 下一个是我啦
Someone planted a bomb on it.
这上面被装了炸弹
Idiot.
笨蛋
Damn it.
糟了
The antenna was broken.
天线断了
Conan, the drone.
柯南 那架飞机
I can't control it anymore. Everybody, run.
没办法控制了 大家快逃
You fool, don't run that way.
笨蛋 别往那边逃
Conan, think!
柯南 快想想办法啊
Shoot!
可恶
Crap!
糟了
Go!
去吧
What's wrong?
怎么回事
Did something explode?
什么东西爆炸了吗
Is it a firework?
是烟火吗
That remote control airplane just blew up!
那架飞机爆炸了
Orange sparks...
橘红色的闪光
That's plastic explsives.
那是塑胶炸弹
What the hell do you want?
你到底想怎么样
Why didn't Kudo come here?
工藤怎么没来
Crap!
糟了
Did he think that a kid like you was enough to defeat me?
他觉得像我这种对手派你这小鬼来就够了吗
A kid like me?
你这小鬼
So he's looking at me from somewhere.
这么说他在某个地方看着我吗
Listen to me carefully.
你仔细听好
There will be another bomb set off at one o'clock.
1点整还有另一个炸弹会爆炸
One o'clock?
1点整
The location is the square in front of Beika station.
地点是米花车站前的广场
Since Kudo didn't come, you should go find it.
既然工藤没来那就由你去找出来吧
Wait.
等一下
How could a kid like me find that with so little information?
你只说这些我还是小孩子怎么会知道嘛
Give me more hints.
再多给我些提示吧
Hello?
喂喂
Under the tree.
树底下
But it was not buried under the tree.
不过可不是埋在树底下
If you don't hurry, it might be taken away by someone else.
你不快去的话说不定会被人拿走哦
Damn it!
可恶
Conan.
柯南
Conan, where are you going?
柯南 你要去哪里
There's still 10 minutes!
还有10分钟
No, there's nothing.
不行 什么都没有
Welcome.
欢迎光临
What's the meaning of "under the tree"?
“树底下”到底是什么意思
"it will be taken away." I don't understand that too.
“会被人拿走”又是什么意思
Anyone with a good heart, please take it away.
好心人请将它带走
So you are abandoned by your owner.
原来你被主人抛弃了
What a poor thing.
真可怜
Don't worry.
不过你不用担心
I'll take you home now.
我这就带你回家
Under the tree.
树底下
The root.
树的根
Root (Nekko).
树根（NEKKO）
Cat (Neko).
猫（NEKO）
Welcome.
谢谢光临
Old lady, please wait a minute!
婆婆 等一下
You moron, didn't you see the red light?!
混蛋 没看到是红灯啊
S-sorry!
对 对不起
Crap!
糟糕
There are only 5 minutes left.
还有5分钟
Shoot.
可恶
4 minutes.
还有4分钟
Great, the car got stuck.
太好了 车被堵住了
What is happening here?
怎么回事
The sun is still there.
还有太阳啊
Right, it must've broken when I crashed earlier.
对了 一定是刚才摔出去的时候被撞坏了
Kid, I need your bike!
小弟弟 自行车借我用一下
Kid?
小弟弟
Do I look younger than him?
难道我比他还小吗
Oh no, the car's starting to move!
不好了 车开始动了
I only have 3 minutes.
还有3分钟
Wait,
对了
I remember there's a big curve to the left on this road.
我记得这条路好像有个向左的大弯道
Are you all right, boy?
你没事吧 小朋友
Excuse me, lady, I need to borrow this cage.
婆婆 这个笼子借我一下
25 seconds left.
还剩下25秒
Boy, did you get hurt?
小朋友 你有没有受伤
Shoot!
可恶
I can't let it explode at this place.
不能让它在这个地方爆炸
What to do?
怎么办
It stopped.
停住了
Okay.
好
I remember there's an empty bank behind the highway.
我记得高速公路的后面有块空地
You are gonna leave this behind?
这个不要了吗
The clock started again!
又开始动了
I want this one!
我决定买这件
Such a bright one!
这么鲜艳啊
Because the color of this shirt...
因为这个衣服的颜色…
The boy who got wounded in order to stop the explosion
（为了阻止炸弹于住宅区爆炸而负伤的少年）
was sent to the police hospital to receive treatment.
（目前已被送往警察医院接受治疗）
Conan woke up.
柯南他醒了
Conan, are you all right?
柯南 你没事吧
This is...
这里是
This is the hospital.
这里是医院
Conan, what happened?
柯南 到底是怎么回事
Don't get too emotional.
不要激动
I need an explanation.
快给我解释清楚
Questions can wait.
问题待会儿再问
Let's call the doctor over.
先去把医生请过来吧
- Conan. - Okay.
柯南 -好
Calm down.
冷静一点
Yes.
是
Don't worry.
不必担心了
The test result shows that
刚才的检查结果表明
there's nothing wrong with his brain waves.
他的脑波并没有出现异常
He'll be able to leave the hospital tomorrow.
明天应该就可以出院了
Thank you very much.
非常感谢
Take care.
请多保重
So, take care.
那么 请多保重
There's something I need to ask you, Conan.
我有事要问你 柯南
Please tell me what happened.
请你把事情的经过告诉我
I see.
原来如此
So you rode a bike to bring the bomb away
这么说你是为了避免别人被爆炸波及
in order to protect others from being blown up.
才会骑车把炸弹带走的吗
Inspector,
警官先生
the criminal can call Shinichi's phone at any time.
犯人会打电话到新一哥哥的手机
But it's not allowed to use cellphones, is it?
但医院不是不能使用手机吗
You don't need to worry about that.
这点你不用担心
This building is separated from the hospital building there.
这里与那边的医院大楼是分开的
There's no electronic equipment to treat diseases here.
这里并没有治疗用的电子仪器
So we can use our cellphones here.
因此可以使用手机
I transferred you here after I had heard what Professor Agasa said.
我是听阿笠博士说了之后才把你转到这里的
Great.
太好了
Also, I broke the bicycle.
还有 那辆自行车被我弄坏了
Mr. Mouri, could you pay for it?
叔叔能不能帮我把车子赔给人家
We'll talk about it later.
这个以后再说
How could you be so reckless?
你这孩子真是乱来啊
You almost died.
你差点就没命了
Sorry.
对不起
Besides, where did Shinichi go?
还有新一到底去哪里了
Wasn't the call for Shinichi?
那个男的不是打电话给新一吗
Because Shinichi happened to have something else to do.
因为新一刚好有别的事情
So, he asked Conan for help.
所以才拜托柯南帮忙的
How could he do that?
怎么会有这种人
Next time I won't be able to forgive him.
下次我一定饶不了他
It's not like I can tell you I am Shinichi.
我总不能说我就是工藤新一吧
By the way, Inspector Megure,
对了 警官先生
did you know what type of bomb it was?
炸弹的种类知道了吗
The bombs on the drone and in the cage
遥控飞机上的炸弹和宠物笼里的炸弹
were both plastic explosives.
都是塑胶炸弹
I knew it.
果然
The orange light mixed with blue sparks
略带蓝色的橘红色闪光
is telltale sign that plastic explosives were involved.
正是塑胶炸弹的特征
I'm afraid these bombs are being made with the stolen materials from Toyo Powder Magazine.
那恐怕就是东洋火药库被盗的炸药
The drone was planted with a bomb with a detonator.
遥控飞机上的是使用了雷管的撞击式炸弹
And the bomb in the cage
至于宠物笼里的炸弹
was connected to a timer.
则是被接上了计时器的定时炸弹
Why did the timer stop moving 16 seconds from the explosion?
那个炸弹为什么会在爆炸前16秒时突然停止呢
About that.
关于这点
It was probably because the timer suddenly malfunctioned,
有可能是计时器突然发生故障
or the criminal stopped the timer remotely for some reason.
或者是犯人出于某种原因以遥控方式将其停止
Those are the only two possibilities that I could think of.
目前只想到这两种可能
The criminal called Kudo particularly,
从犯人特地打电话给工藤这点来看
so he either wants to challenge Shinichi Kudo, the high school detective,
他可能是想挑战高中生名侦探工藤新一
or has a personal grudge against him.
不然就是和他有私人恩怨
According to our investigation,
根据调查
all the criminals in cases solved by Shinichi Kudo
工藤新一所解决的案件的犯人
are in prison right now.
现在都还在监狱里
So it might be those criminals' families or loved ones.
这么说就是犯人的亲人或恋人了
Anyway, we already started looking according to the sketch they made.
总之我们正根据他们所画的这张特征图在进行调查
Conan, it's this one. The sketch is very lifelike.
柯南 就是这个 画得很像哦
You did a great job.
画得很好呢
We drew this together.
这是我们3个人一起画的
You've drawn all these features.
特征都表现出来了嘛
But I don't remember this guy at all.
不过我完全没有印象
The criminal used a voice-changing device,
犯人还用变声器改变了声音
so maybe it's someone I know.
说不定是我认识的人
Inspector,
警官先生
which case that Shinichi solved
过去新一所解决的案件里
got the most publicity?
最受到社会关注的是哪一件呢
I think it should be
我觉得应该是
the case of the mayor of Nishitamashi.
西多摩市冈本市长的那件案子吧
A 25-year-old secretary living in Nishitamashi
住在西多摩市的25岁的粉领族
was driven over by the mayor's son.
被市长的儿子开车撞死的案件
At first, we thought her death was merely an accident,
开始我们都认为那是单纯的交通意外
but Kudo found the case very suspicious.
但是工藤却对其有所怀疑
A cigarette butt was found at the crime scene next to the victim's body.
这截烟蒂是在案发现场被害人的尸体旁发现的
Your saliva was found on the surface.
警方检验出上面有你的唾液
You're the one who threw it, right?
这是你丢的吧
Yes.
对
After I hit her,
我在撞了她以后
I ran out of my car in panic.
慌张地从驾驶座跑出来
I think I might have thrown it unconsciously at that time.
我想就是那时无意中丢掉的吧
I see.
原来如此
Judging from its length,
从它的长度来看
I think the accident happened not long after you lit the cigarette.
在你点火之后不久就发生了意外吧
That's right.
没错
The accident happened right after I lit it.
刚点着火就发生意外了
You used a lighter?
用的打火机吗
Yes.
对
What kind of lighter did you use?
你是用的什么打火机呢
The cigarette lighter on the car.
我用的是车上的点烟器
Then please sit back on the driver's seat
那么请你坐到驾驶座上
and show it to me again, OK?
示范一次给我看好吗
You only need to repeat your movements.
你只要做一下动作就可以了
But please fasten your seatbelt.
不过麻烦你把安全带系好
Okay.
是
Here.
给你
Please use this box of cigarettes to demonstrate.
请用这盒烟来示范吧
It's the same brand as
跟当时掉在现场的烟蒂
the one you dropped at the crime scene.
是同一牌子的香烟
Stop.
停
That's right.
没错
If you want to get the cigarette light from the driver's seat,
要从驾驶座拿点烟器的话
you have to reach out your left hand.
必须要伸长左手才可能拿得到
But only the fingerprints of your right hand were found on this lighter.
但是这个点烟器上只有你右手的指纹
Can you explain why is that, Mr. Kohei?
请问这是怎么回事 浩平先生
I think I used my own lighter.
我好像用的是自己的打火机
No.
不对
You left it at home when you came out,
你出门时把它忘在家里没带出来
and your father doesn't smoke.
而你父亲是不抽烟的
That night, you used the cigarette lighter on the passenger seat.
案发当晚你是在副驾驶座上使用的点烟器
Which means, you were sitting next to your father, who was driving.
也就是坐在当时在开车的父亲旁边
You two wiped off your father's fingerprints from all the other places.
其他地方的指纹都擦掉了
Even the position of the seat and the angle of the rearview mirror were adjusted.
就连座位的位置以及后视镜的角度也被调整过
But you missed the cigarette lighter.
不过你们似乎忽略了点烟器的部分
Mayor Okamoto.
冈本市长
Kohei, my son,
我儿子浩平他
he considered my position as the mayor
因为考虑到我这个市长的立场
and decided to take the fall for me.
所以才决定替我顶罪
Actually, I'm the one who drove the car that day.
其实当天开车的人是我
I am so sorry.
真的很对不起
Father!
爸爸
Because of that case,
因为那件案子的关系
Mayor Okamoto was ousted.
冈本市长黯然下台
The new City Construction Project of Nishitamashi which he initiated was also put on hold.
他策划的西多摩市新城镇建造工程也就此搁置
Inspector,
警官
is it possible that Mayor Okamoto's son has been holding a grudge because of that?
难道是冈本市长的儿子对那次的事件怀恨在心
I remember that he's a student in the electronic engineering department.
我记得他好像是电子工程系的学生
I'll look into it.
我马上去调查
Apart from these,
除了这些呢
do you have any other impressions about the criminal?
关于犯人你们还有其他的印象吗
Anything you can think of.
什么都可以
Well...
这个嘛
The smell.
气味
I smelled something very strong
我闻到香香的气味
when he handed the drone to Mitsuhiko.
当他把遥控飞机给光彦的时候
Really?
是吗
Why didn't I smell that?
我怎么没有闻到那种气味
Me neither.
我也没有闻到
Could it be a fragrance from the cosmetics he used?
香香的气味难道是化妆品吗
I don't know.
不知道
But it wasn't like perfume,
不过好像跟香水不太一样
that fragrant smell.
香香的气味
I see.
我知道了
If you remember any other clues,
如果你们想到了其他的线索
just tell me right away.
马上告诉我
Okay.
好
Now we should probably go home now.
那我们差不多也该回家了吧
Yeah.
也是啊
Conan has gotten a lot better now.
柯南已经好多了
If there's anything you need me to do, I'll come here right away.
如果有什么事的话我会马上赶来的
Thanks.
谢谢
Conan is so lucky.
柯南真好
I want to be hospitalized too.
我们也好想住院啊
I never realized you were so popular.
想不到你这么受欢迎呢
You're good with the girls, little boy.
挺有一套的嘛 你这个小鬼
You have no idea how I feel.
你根本就不懂我的感受
Then, we'll be leaving now.
那么我们就先回去了
See you, Conan.
再见 柯南
Thank you.
谢谢
By the way,
话说回来
where did Kudo go at such a critical moment?
在这么重要的时候工藤到底去哪里了
Wait, Conan!
等等 柯南
Listen, if it's the criminal, just hand the phone to me.
听好 如果是犯人就把电话给我
Hello.
喂
I can't believe you found the bomb.
想不到你找到了那个炸弹
You deserve a reward.
值得奖励
But playtime with the kid is over.
但是小孩做游戏的时间已经结束了
Tell Kudo to come.
叫工藤过来
That's right.
没错
From now on, the adults will do the talking.
现在开始就是大人的时间
Who are you? Where is Kudo?
你是谁 工藤呢
Kudo is not here.
工藤不在这里
I'll deal with you.
让我来对付你
I am the famous detective, Kogoro Mouri.
我是名侦探毛利小五郎
Fine.
也好
I'll say this just once. Listen carefully.
我只说一次 给我听好了
I planted 5 bombs on the Kyoto Circle Line.
我在东都环状线上装了5个炸弹
Five...
5个
bombs?!
炸弹
From 4 p.m. today,
从今天下午4点开始
the bombs will explode if the train's speed drops lower than 60km/h.
电车时速若低于60公里炸弹就会爆炸
Also, if the bombs are not removed before sunset, they will explode anyway.
另外 日落时还没拆除的话炸弹也会爆炸
I'll only give you one hint:
我只给你一个提示
The five bombs have been placed in "X the XX" on the Kyoto Circle Line.
5个炸弹都安装在东都环状线的“XX之X”那里
Each X represents a single character.
每个“X”都代表一个汉字
Good luck, Detective Mouri.
那么请加油吧 毛利名侦探
He-he's just bluffing, right?
他 他只是在吓唬我们吧
How could he put bombs on the circle line?
怎么可能把炸弹装在环状线上
No, he was dead serious.
不 他是认真的
The detonated explosive devices will be activated at 4 p.m.
引爆装置大概被设定为下午4点启动
Then, if the train's speed drops lower than 60 km/h,
然后 若电车的时速低于60公里
the bombs will go off.
就会真的发生爆炸
Anyway,
总之
I have to contact the headquarters right away.
我必须马上跟总部联络
This is Megure.
我是目暮
I agree with Inspector Megure.
我的看法也跟目暮警官一样
But,
不过
what is the criminal's purpose?
犯人的目的到底是什么
Why is he doing this?
他为什么要这样做
We made it!
还好及时赶上了
We got super lucky today!
可见我们今天很幸运
(Kyoto Railway Dispatching Station)
[东都铁道调度总站]
There are bombs on the circle line?
环状线上被装了炸弹
Yes, we just received an emergency notice from the Metropolitan Police Department.
是的 刚才收到了警视厅的紧急通知
I see.
知道了
I'll stop all the trains and get those carriages inspected.
我立刻让所有电车停驶并进行检查
No!
不行
We can't stop the train.
绝对不能让车停下来
After 4 p.m., if the train's speed is lower than 60km/h,
电车在下午4点后如果时速不满60公里的话
the bombs will explode.
听说炸弹就会爆炸
What?!
你说什么
There are only three minutes left.
下午4点的话只剩下3分钟了
Make sure that all the trains on the circle line remain at a speed of 60km/h.
立刻让环状线上所有电车时速保持在60公里
No, make it 70 km/h.
不 让所有的车以时速70公里行驶
What about the trains which are parked at the station?
停在车站里的车呢
Get them to leave the station now.
立刻发车
And the trains which are about to pull in?
即将进站的车呢
Don't let them stop.
直接过站
In a word, none of the trains can be allowed stop before the bombs are found.
总之在找出炸弹之前所有车都不准停下来
Hurry up!
快点去啊
Yes, sir.
是 我知道了
Emergency announcement
紧急指令
Attention, all the trains,
各列车请注意
an unidentified man has planted bombs on the circle line.
环状线上已被不明歹徒安装了炸弹
The bombs will explode if the train's speed falls under 60 km/h.
若电车时速低于60公里就会立刻爆炸
Please keep the train's speed at 70 km/h.
所有车请保持时速70公里
Repeat.
重复
An unidentified man has planted bombs on the circle line.
环状线上已被不明歹徒安装了炸弹
The bombs will explode if the train's speed falls under 60 km/h.
若电车时速低于60公里就会立刻爆炸
Please keep the train's speed at 70 km/h.
所有车请保持时速70公里
Isn't this kind weird?
你们不觉得这班车很奇怪吗
What's so weird about it, Genta?
有什么奇怪呢 元太
We're about to arrive at Beika station, but the train just started speeding up.
就快到米花车站了可速度却越来越快
Passengers, may I have your attention please.
各位乘客请注意
Due to an unexpected accident,
因为突发事故
this train will not stop at Beika Station.
本班车经过下一站米花车站时将不停靠
What does that mean, an unexpected accident?
突发事故是什么意思
The Kyoto Circle Line train which is supposed to stop at No.1 platform
原定在1号站台停靠的东都环状线外环列车
will not stop at this station.
因突发事故将不在本站停靠
Is that so? I see.
是吗 我明白了
None of the trains have exploded yet.
到目前为止还没有电车发生爆炸
I've got it, Inspector Megure.
我知道了 目暮警官
What did you figure out?
你知道什么了
The "X the XX" that the criminal mentioned on the phone
犯人在电话里提到的“XX之X”
must be Under the Train Seat.
指的就是“座位之下”
or On the Overhead Shelf.
要不然就是“架子之上”吧
That's where the criminal put the bombs!
犯人把炸弹装在了那里
By that logic, Under the Train Carriage also makes sense.
那“车身之下”也说得通吧
Oh, that's right...
对啊
By the way, if Ayumi and the boys were going back to Beika Chou,
对了 步美他们要回米花町的话
they be would taking the circle line from the green station right about now.
也会从绿台车站搭乘环状线回去吧
Repeat.
重复
This train will not stop at any station for the time being.
本班车暂时不会在任何车站停靠
Plus, if you find anything suspicious on the train,
另外 如果在车内发现可疑物品
please don't touch it and instead inform the conductor at once.
一定不要随意触摸 并请立刻通知车长
Anything suspicious, what does that mean?
可疑物品是什么
It means something weird.
就是奇怪的东西嘛
Of course I know that. I mean, what could they be thinking we'd find?
我当然知道 我是说可疑物品指的是什么
That's-
这个
Ayumi, are you there?
步美 你听得到吗
Conan, I'm here.
柯南 我听到了
Where are you right now?
你现在在哪里
On the circle line.
在环状线上
So you really are there.
果然
Conan, what is going on here?
柯南 这到底是怎么回事
Did someone plant a bomb on the train too?
难道车上也被人安装了炸弹之类的东西吗
Don't worry.
你们不用担心
It's nothing like that.
没有那回事
So,
所以说
those bombs might not be put on the trains on the circle line!
那些炸弹不一定是装在了环状线的电车上
Bombs?
炸弹
I knew it!
果然
So are we going to die?
那我们不是死定了吗
You won't die!
你们不会死的
I'll find the location of the bombs.
我一定会把炸弹的位置找到
Conan...
柯南
Damn it!
可恶
How could we leave everything to Conan?
怎么能只交给柯南一个人呢
We have to do something too!
我们也要加油啊
It's time for the Junior Detective Squad to take action!
这种时候该我们少年侦探团行动了
Junior...
少年
Detective Squad?
侦探团
That's-that's right.
对 对啊
The bombs seemed to have been planted on the trains.
炸弹好像是被装在了电车上
All right, go, Junior Detective Squad!
好 少年侦探团出发
Alright!
好
You guys-!
你们几个
Jeez, how could they cut off the phone lines?
竟然切断了通话
Are they going to be all right?
他们不要紧吧
Okay, I see.
好 我知道了
There's a joint operation center formed at headquarters.
总部已经成立了联合指挥中心
I need to go to Kyoto Railway Dispatching Station.
我要到东都铁道调度总站去
Are you going with me?
你也一起去吗
Right, absolutely.
好 我愿意同行
It's already half past four.
目前已经过了4点半
Now, everyone, please take a look at
各位请看
the Kyoto Circle Line beneath me.
位于我下方的东都环状线全线
For more than 30 minutes, none of the trains have stopped at any station.
目前已经超过30分钟没有车停站了
The explanation which
关于这次的异常状况
the Kyoto Railway and the Metropolitan Police Department have given
东都铁道与警视厅
is that there has been an emergency.
只对外公布说有紧急状况发生
The police couldn't hide the truth for more than 30 minutes.
警方对社会封锁消息的时间30分钟就是极限了吧
I borrowed it from a nurse.
这是我从护士那里借来的
Let's watch it in the patient ward.
到病房里看比较方便吧
It is impossible to design a bomb
时速低于60公里就会爆炸
which will explode when its moves at a speed below 60 km/h.
就设计来说的确有可能
But... how could they make a bomb that would explode
但是日落后没有拆除也会爆炸
automatically after sunset?
这到底是怎么做到的
Why would it explode specifically after the sunset?
为什么日落后就会爆炸
Does it have something to do with the light in the train?
难道跟电车的车灯有关吗
Sorry to have kept you waiting.
让你们久等了
Please enjoy.
请慢用
That shirt looks nice.
那件衣服很不错嘛
Ran, you look good in red too.
小兰你也蛮适合红色的
Thanks.
谢谢
Shinichi's lucky color for this month is red, just like mine.
这个月我跟新一的幸运色都是红色呢
Speaking of which, I haven't seen Shinichi for a long time either.
说起来我和新一也很久没见面了
Can I go with you?
我跟你一起去吧
But the movie we are going to watch is kind of boring.
可是我们要看的电影很无聊
And he's a boring guy too.
而且他那个人也很无趣
I'm just joking!
玩笑啦 玩笑
Why would I want to be a third wheel?
谁要去当你们的电灯泡嘛
Don't take it so seriously.
人家说什么你马上就当真
I just like to make fun of you.
捉弄你真是好玩
Come on, Sonoko.
园子你真是的
Anyway, I'm surprised that your dad agreed to let you watch a midnight movie with Shinichi.
不过你老爸居然答应让你们去看午夜场电影啊
He did object,
虽然他很反对
but I wouldn't listen to him anyway.
不过我才不管呢
Perhaps he is arguing with Conan about what to eat tonight right now.
他大概正在和柯南讨论今晚吃什么吧
So,
这么说来
nothing suspicious was found on any of the trains?
车内并没有发现任何可疑物品吗
Yes.
是的
There are 21 trains on the line now.
目前行驶中的21列电车
We already asked the conductors to check every coach.
我们已经请车长仔细检查过整个车厢了
There's no package which doesn't have an owner.
所有行李都找到了主人
So, how's everything going with you guys?
对了 你们那边呢
We checked the footage from the security cameras along the circle line.
我们看了沿线的摄像机拍下的录像带
But we didn't find anything which looks like a bomb under the train.
列车下面也没有发现任何疑似炸弹的物品
I see.
这样啊
So where could the bombs be planted?
那么炸弹到底会在哪里
Bad news, minister.
不好了 部长
There's an uproar on the trains.
车上的乘客开始出现骚动了
What?
什么
When is this train going to stop?
这车到底要开到什么时候啊
Stop the train!
快把车停下来
My kid has been saying that he has a stomachache!
我的孩子一直说肚子疼
Please let us get off the train!
求求你让我们下车好不好
What is that suspicious object?
可疑物品到底是什么
Did someone plant the bombs here?
不会是被人安装了炸弹吧
B-bombs?
炸 炸弹
Are you kidding me? I'm getting off the train!
开什么玩笑 我要下车了
Stop what you're doing! It's too dangerous! Please calm down!
别这样 这太危险了 请冷静
You'll be badly injured if you jump out!
跳车的话会受重伤的
Chief, the situation is out of control.
调度长 我们快控制不住了
Please hold on a little longer.
请你们再撑一下
Mouri, you still haven't figured out a way to find the bombs?
毛利老弟 还没有办法找出炸弹吗
The sun will go down in one and a half hours.
还有一个半小时就到日落的时候了
The bombs will explode after sunset.
但是日落后炸弹就会爆炸
That's exactly the opposite of the skateboard I invented.
简直和我发明的滑板完全相反
The skateboard is solar-powered,
滑板的动力来源是太阳能
so it can't be used after the sun goes down.
所以日落后就不能用了
Solar, the sun...
日 太阳
I got it!
我明白了
I got it, professor!
我明白了 博士
This is Megure.
我是目暮
Inspector, this is Kudo.
警官 我是工藤
Kudo, I've been waiting for you to call.
工藤 等你很久了
I've heard the whole story from Professor Hiroshi.
情况我都从阿笠博士那里听说了
The bombs were not set
炸弹所在的位置
under the seats of the circle line trains or on the shelves.
不是环状线电车的座位之下 也不是架子之上
They are definitely not under the trains either.
更不是什么车身之下
They were planted between the rail tracks.
而是在铁轨之间
Between the rail tracks?
铁轨之间
If those bombs aren't exposed to the sun for a certain period of time, they will explode.
那些炸弹如果在一定时间内没照到阳光就会爆炸
When the circle line train passes above the bombs,
当环状线电车从炸弹上方通过时
the sunlight will be blocked for a few seconds.
列车完全通过前的几秒钟阳光会被遮住
The length of each coach is 20 meters,
每节车厢的长度以20米计算
so the total length of 10 coaches should be 200 meters.
10节车厢就是200米
If the train is going at a speed of 60 km/h,
若时速保持在60公里
which is 16.7m/s,
就相当于秒速16.7米
it will take 12 seconds for the train to travel 200 meters.
也就是说 车行200米需要12秒
So, if the train passes over them at a speed of 60 km/h,
而炸弹爆炸的最长缓冲时间
the timers on the bombs will be reset again.
正是以时速60公里通过所需的时间
So please tell the drivers to drive the trains to other lines.
所以请立刻将环状线的电车移到其他线路上
As long as the trains leave the circle line and stop,
只要让列车从环状线上离开
there wouldn't be any explosion.
停车就不会有危险了
I see.
我知道了
Minister Sakaguchi,
坂口部长
you heard that, right?
你应该都听到了吧
Three minutes later, Train 11 will be transferred to the freight line of Shibahama Station.
3分钟后将11号车转入芝浜站的货车线上
Now get ready.
立刻开始准备
Train 11.
11号车
Please change tracks in 3 minutes.
3分钟后切换轨道
The line of Shibahama station is confirmed. Change tracks now.
芝浜站线路确认 开始并轨
The freight train will be transferred to the emergency evacuation track.
货运列车马上转往紧急疏散轨道
Train 11 passed Kawashina station.
11号车通过川品站
Train 10 passed Shibahama station.
10号车通过芝浜站
Switch the track.
切换轨道
Now, begin to slow down.
现在开始减速
68 km/h.
68km
66 km/h.
66km
63 km
63km
60 km
60km
58 km.
58km
Is anything unusual happening there?
有没有异常情况
Sir, nothing's happening.
报告 没有异常状况
Great.
很好
Now keep reducing the speed and stop at the next station.
继续减速然后在下个货物站停车
Yes.
明白
We did it.
成功了
No, it's too early to celebrate.
不 现在还不能大意
There are still 20 trains on the circle line now.
因为环状线上还有20列电车正在行驶
Nothing abnormal on Train 9.
9号车没有异常状况
Nothing abnormal on Train 20.
20号车没有异常状况
There's only one train left.
只剩下一列电车了
This is Train 10.
这里是10号车
We are moving at a speed of 55 km/h.
目前时速55公里
Nothing unusual is happening.
没有任何异常
Perfect.
太好了
Great, we did it.
太好了 我们成功了
Our chief is truly outstanding.
真是出色的指挥调度啊
Thanks for your hard work, everyone.
辛苦大家了
Now it's our turn.
现在开始就是我们的工作了
Great, we could finally get off the train.
太好了 我们终于可以下车了
I'll never tire myself out trying to catch a train again.
我以后再也不会拼了命去赶电车了
Really? That's great.
是吗 太好了
Conan, are you the one who found the bombs?
是柯南你找出了炸弹的位置吗
No,
不是
it was Shinichi.
是新一哥哥发现的
Actually,
老实说
we still haven't found the bombs yet.
炸弹到现在都还没有找到
They were set on the tracks before 4 p.m.
炸弹被安装的时间是下午4点之前
at a place where the sunlight wouldn't be blocked by the buildings or walls.
位置是在没有大楼或墙挡住阳光的地方
Pay attention to the sun's position when you are searching for the bombs,
搜寻时必须注意太阳的位置
don't let your shadows cover the bombs.
避免让自己的影子遮住炸弹
I need you to be very careful.
大家要特别小心
Found it.
发现炸弹了
I see.
我知道了
The 5 bombs were all removed safely.
那5个炸弹听说都已经安全回收了
Great.
太好了
Perfect.
好啊
It's exactly like Kudo deduced.
一切就如工藤所推理的一样
The sun will go down in 15 minutes.
距离日落还有15分钟
Talk about a close call.
真是千钧一发
It's too soon to relax.
但是要高兴还太早了
The quantity of the explosive load inside those bombs
那些炸弹的装药量
is only a quarter of the explosive materials
与几天前被盗的炸药数量相比
which were stolen.
听说仅为总量的四分之一
It means that
这么说
the criminal still has three quarters of the explosives ready to put into play.
剩下的四分之三仍在犯人手上
Sorry I'm late.
我来迟了
How's the investigation going?
查得如何
Yes.
是
Mayor Okamoto's son, Kohei Okamoto
冈本市长的儿子浩平
flew to Izu this morning.
今天一大早就到伊豆去了
So this has nothing to do with him.
这么说就跟他无关了
Yes.
是的
Well, about the bomb incident this time...
那个 关于这次的炸弹事件
It's been solved.
已经解决了
We have to thank Kudo for this.
这次要感谢工藤
Our next problems are the rest of the bombs and the criminal.
接下来的问题就是剩下的炸药和犯人了
What we know at this point is that
目前我们所知道的是
the criminal's residence can't be somewhere
犯人绝对不可能住在环状线上
near the places where the five bombs were planted.
那5个被安装炸弹的地点附近
I think we can all agree with that, right?
大概是这样吧
You don't think so?
难道不是吗
If the bombs explode, the whole train would be blown off the tracks.
炸弹爆炸的话整列车都会被炸飞
How could he plant the bombs near his home?
怎么可能安装在自己家附近
At that time,
那个时候
did he stop the timer in the cage
他之所以会让宠物笼里的计时器暂停
for the same reason?
会不会是因为同样的理由
There's a children's park and an apartment near that place.
那附近有儿童公园和公寓
That's right.
没错
The criminal must live in that apartment.
犯人一定是住在那栋公寓里
Okay.
好的
Let's head to that apartment now.
我们这就出发到那栋公寓去
You found nothing.
没找到
Yes.
对啊
We searched not only that apartment
不仅是那栋公寓
but also all the places nearby.
我们连附近的地方也查过了
We found no-one who's relevant to the case.
他们都跟案子无关
Is that so?
是这样吗
Inspector.
警官先生
What kind of place were the bombs planted at on the circle line?
环状线上的炸弹被安装在了什么样的地方呢
What kind of place?
什么样的地方
I think it was the places near the residential area.
都是在普通的住宅区附近
Wait,
对了
one was set on the bridge
有一个被装在了桥上
above the Sumita Canal.
在隅田运河上
The bridge?
桥上
You mean that bridge?
不就是这座桥吗
(Bombs on Kyoto Circle Line)
[东都环状线炸弹警告]
Wait,
等等
I remember seeing this photo in Professor Moriya's gallery.
我记得森谷教授的展览室里有这张照片
Isn't that bridge designed by Professor Moriya?
那座桥不就是森谷教授设计的吗
I think so.
好像是啊
That's right.
没错
It was indeed designed by Teiji Moriya.
的确是森谷帝二设计的
That's bridge was fully constructed on the 58th year of Showa period.
那座桥于昭和58年建成
It was constructed with stones like British bridges instead of the usual iron,
它不是铁桥而是由石块搭建而成的英式桥梁
which attracted widespread attention.
所以在当时引起了广泛的关注
Teiji Moriya won the Japanese Construction Association's Best New Architect award
森谷帝二也因为这座桥而得到了
for designing that bridge.
日本建筑协会的新人奖
You sure know a lot of things.
你知道得真多啊
That's because I'm interested in architecture.
因为我对建筑学很感兴趣
(Next is the news about the serial arson)
（接着报道连续纵火的新闻）
(The Metropolitan Police Department...)
（警视厅…）
Turn that off. We'll get distracted.
不要看了 会分心
Fine.
好
I just remembered.
我想起来了
Mr. Kurokawa's house which was set on fire a few days ago
前几天被人纵火的黑川宅
was also designed by Professor Moriya.
好像也是森谷教授设计的
I wonder who designed the houses which were
那些在连续纵火事件中被烧的房子
burnt down by that serial arsonist.
不知道是谁设计的
We might find something interesting
若去调查一下说不定会发现有趣的事哦
if we look into it.
有趣的事
I'll leave you here then.
到这里就可以了
Thanks for your company for today.
谢谢你今天一直陪着我
Don't forget to give me the details later.
之后要好好地向我报告哦
You should at least kiss him.
最少也要和他接吻啊
It's 9 o'clock.
9点了
There's only one hour left.
还有1小时
What did you say?
你说什么
They were all designed by Professor Moriya.
全都是森谷教授设计的
Yes.
对
The houses which were burnt down, including
从黑川宅开始
Mr. Kurokawa's house,
水岛宅 安田宅 阿久津宅
Mr. Mizushima's house, Mr. Yasuda's house, and Mr. Akutsu's house
这些被人纵火的房子
were all designed by Professor Moriya when he was around 30.
全都是森谷教授在30多岁时设计的作品
That doesn't look like a coincidence to me.
怎么看都不像是巧合
Perhaps the reason why the criminal planted the bomb on that bridge is that
说不定犯人在环状线上装炸弹的真正目的
he wanted to blow up that specific bridge.
是要炸毁那座桥呢
That bridge?
那座桥
It's very possible.
的确有可能
Maybe the bomber and the serial arsonist are the same person,
说不定与连续纵火犯是同一个人
taking aim at Professor Moriya's works.
目标都是森谷教授的作品
That's right.
对了
I got it, inspector.
我明白了 警官
Maybe the criminal is Professor Moriya's enemy or someone jealous of his success.
犯人大概是与森谷教授有仇或嫉妒他成功的人
The challenge he gave to Shinichi
他对新一的挑战
was merely a camouflage.
只是一种障眼法而已
So that's what it is.
原来如此
Your deduction seems quite plausible.
这种可能性的确很高
I feel the same way.
我也有同感
The arsonist used a hand-made ignition device.
这一连串的纵火案都是用的自制引火装置
On second thought, he and the bomber do have one thing in common.
仔细想想的确和炸弹疑犯有相同点
That the works which were burnt down were all designed by Moriya when he was around 30?
被破坏的都是他30多岁时的作品吗
Fine.
好吧
Let's go talk to Professor Moriya.
我们就先去找森谷教授谈谈
Mouri, please lead the way.
毛利老弟 麻烦你带路吧
I don't think I remember the way.
他家怎么走来着
Uncle, I know how to get there.
叔叔 我知道怎么去
I'll be your guide.
让我来带路吧
Cut the nonsense, you haven't...
胡说什么 你还没…
I've already recovered.
我早就已经好了
Hurry, hurry.
快点 快点
Wait.
等一下
Please, Shinichi.
拜托你了 新一
Mr. Mouri,
毛利先生
that's the place where the timer stopped clicking.
前面就是上次炸弹的计时器暂时停止的地方
The children's park?
儿童公园吗
Come on.
真是的
We've spent a lot of time searching for those bombs here.
为了那几个炸弹白费了许多工夫来这里调查
I see.
原来如此
What an unexpected coincidence.
这样的巧合的确有点不可思议
Do you have any idea of what kind of person
对于可能做出这种事的人
might do that?
不知道你有没有印象呢
Well.
这个嘛
That's a photo of me when I was 10, Conan.
那是我10岁时的照片 柯南
The people in the picture are my parents.
和我在一起的是我的父母
I heard your father was an outstanding man, Professor Moriya.
森谷教授的父亲听说是个很了不起的人
He was a well-known architect around the world.
他是一位享誉世界的建筑师
He had been active in the British architecture scene.
过去主要是活跃在英国的建筑界
I love the structures he designed the most.
我最喜欢他设计的建筑物了
I remember that he passed away at...
我记得他过世是在…
In a catastrophic fire inside a villa
在15年前别墅的一场大火中
with my mother...
和我的母亲一起…
I inherited this house after the fire.
这栋房子就是我在那个时候继承的遗产
I remember that it was ever since then that
我记得好像就是从那时起
Professor Moriya's designs started to draw everyone's attention.
森谷教授的设计开始受到大家的注意
That's right.
没错
The smell.
这个气味
Is it possible that...
难道说
Professor Moriya,
森谷教授
do you know anyone who might want to commit these crimes?
你知道有什么人可能会犯下这些案子呢
Well.
这个嘛
The works he designed at the age around 30 start from here.
他30多岁时的作品是从这里开始的
Kurokawa's House, Mizushima's House, Yasuda's House and Akutsu's House
黑川宅 水岛宅 安田宅以及阿久津宅
and this bridge.
还有就是这座桥
Wait, the bridge...!
等等 这座桥…
There's no doubt about it!
一定错不了
The structures I designed when I was young are not mature enough.
年轻的时候毕竟不够成熟
Please don't look at those too long.
还是请你们别看了
No way. How's that even possible?
不会吧 怎么可能有这种事
But the smell.
但是刚才那个气味
Was it already here last time I came?
我上次来的时候有这个吗
The new town of my dreams, Nishitamashi.
我梦想中的新城镇 西多摩市
Come to think of it...
这么说来
Because of that case, Mayor Okamoto was ousted.
因为那件案子的关系 冈本市长黯然下台
The new City Construction Project of Nishitamashi which he initiated was also put on hold.
他策划的西多摩市新城镇建造工程也就此搁置
I see.
原来如此
The one who was in charge of that construction project must be Professor Moriya.
当年策划这个工程的就是森谷教授
This new town is completely symmetrical.
是个完全对称风格的新城镇
It's the same streetlamp as the one in the children's park!
跟儿童公园的路灯是一样的
That explains why he did that...
原来如此 所以那个时候他才…
Then he is the criminal,
犯人果然就是他
but I don't have any proof.
但是我没有证据
I have to take a chance now.
事到如今也只能和他赌一把了
This will come in handy.
这个东西正好能用
Next, I'll need a pair of scissors, a tape and a felt-tip pen.
然后是剪刀 胶带和水性笔
A lighter?
打火机
So,
是吗
you have no idea.
你也不知道是谁啊
Sorry I couldn't be of help.
没能帮上忙真的很抱歉
Anyway, if you remember anything, just call us.
那么 如果你想起什么的话请跟我们联络
Where did Conan go?
柯南去哪里了
Sorry, I need to get that.
抱歉 我接个电话
Yes, this is Megure.
我是目暮
Oh, Kudo!
工藤啊
I see.
我知道了
You want us to go to the gallery, right?
现在立刻到展览室集合就行了吧
Professor Moriya,
森谷教授
excuse me, can we visit your gallery?
不好意思 可以让我们参观一下展览室吗
Okay, no problem.
好 我知道了
Can I go to my study before that?
在那之前我可以先去一下书房吗
Of course.
当然可以
Sorry to have kept you waiting.
让各位久等了
Please follow me.
请跟我来
The gallery is on the second floor.
展览室就在2楼
Please come in.
来 请进
This is Megure.
我是目暮
That's right. We are at the gallery now.
对 我们到展览室了
Inspector Megure,
目暮警官
please put me on speaker, OK?
请按下扩音键让大家都听到好吗
I already know who set the fire and planted the bombs.
我已经知道纵火案与炸弹事件的犯人了
Really?
是真的吗
Who is that?
那犯人到底是谁
Wait!
等等
I know it too!
我也知道是谁了
It's you, Officer Shiratori!
真正的凶手就是你 白鸟警官
What?!
你说什么
You respect Professor Moriya's father a lot
一直非常尊敬森谷教授父亲的你
and have doubts about the cause of his death.
对他的死因非常怀疑
The thing which got you most suspicious is that
而怀疑的焦点就集中到
Professor Moriya began to gain fame after his father died.
在父亲死后突然就出名了的儿子身上
You think that Professor Moriya set the fire in the villa in order to kill his father.
你怀疑是森谷教授在别墅纵火烧死了自己的父亲
Since you are convinced of that thought,
在你确信这点之后
you started to set all of Professor Moriya's works on fire one after another.
你就将森谷教授的作品一个一个地烧掉了
Your respect for the father became your hatred for the son.
你对父亲的尊敬此时却变成了对儿子的报复
What's more, every time the criminal called, you happened to be absent.
而且每次犯人打电话来时你都刚好不在现场
W-wait a minute!
等 等一下啊
Shinichi!
新一
Is that what you are going to say?
你是不是也想这么说啊
Not at all.
不是
What?
什么
The serial of crimes
这一连串的事件
were not committed by Professor Moriya's enemy.
并不是和森谷教授有仇的人犯下的罪行
The criminal is the one who
犯人就是最近被纵火的4栋房子
designed the houses which were burnt down lately and that bridge. Professor Moriya,
以及那座桥的设计者森谷教授本人
it was you.
就是你
What?!
什么
Idiot!
笨蛋
Which architect in the world would destroy their own works?
世界上哪有建筑师会破坏自己的作品啊
As an architect's son, he's also gifted in architecture.
从小就继承了父亲的建筑师才华的森谷教授
As he reached 30, he already began to make a name for himself as a young architect.
30岁刚出头就以年轻建筑师的身份崭露头角
Er, hello?
喂喂
After that, he won the Japanese Construction Association's Best New Architect award
然后他又因设计环状线的石桥
for designing the stone bridge on the circle line.
得到了日本建筑协会的新人奖
After that, Professor Moriya created lots of works
在那之后
in that new construction style.
不断创造出许多新建筑样式的森谷教授
But one day it suddenly occurred to him,
某天突然想到
No, I should say, he had had that idea for a long time...
不 应该说很早以前就有了这个想法
He wanted to destroy the works he designed when he was young.
他想毁掉自己年轻时设计的一些作品
He has revealed that thought somewhat at the tea party.
这从之前的茶会上教授的话中就可略知一二
A lot of young architects today
现在有不少年轻的建筑师
have no acknowledgement of beauty.
根本缺乏对美的意识
They have to be more responsible to their works.
他们必须对自己的作品更有责任感才行
Which means, he wanted to put those words into practice.
也就是说他实践了自己的那番话
That makes sense.
说起来好像有这么回事
Wait.
等一下
You weren't there that day, how did you know...
那天你又没去怎么会知道…
Next, everyone,
接下来 各位
please take a look at the pictures on the wall.
请仔细看看墙上的照片
Watch closely at Mr. Kurokawa's House, Mizushima's House, Yasuda's House and Akutsu's House
仔细观察黑川宅 水岛宅 安田宅 阿久津宅
and the stone bridge.
以及那座石桥
Though they are all structures in British classical style,
虽然都是英国古典风格的建筑
but there is one thing I don't know if you may have noticed.
但是各位有没有注意到一件事情
I think they are all very beautiful.
我认为每一个都是优秀的建筑啊
These structures are not completely symmetrical.
这些并不是完全对称建筑
That's right.
没错
The structures are not totally symmetrical.
那些的确不是完全的左右对称建筑
Perhaps Professor Moriya had to submit to
可能是因为业主的要求或者建筑基准法的规定
the requests of the house owners or the Construction Standard Law.
使得他当时不得不妥协
However, for a perfectionist like Professor Moriya,
但这对一向主张完美主义的森谷教授来说
that was intolerable.
却是一件难以容忍的事
Right at that time,
就在那个时候
for the first time, there was a setback appearing in his
他那一帆风顺的建筑师生涯中
architectural career that had been so successful all this whole time.
又第一次出现了挫折
The new town construction project of Nishitamashi which he spent a lot of time on
花费长时间完成的西多摩市新城镇建造计划
was put on hold because the mayor had stepped down.
却因为市长的下台而被搁置
I see. So this was Professor Moriya's design too.
原来如此 这也是森谷教授设计的作品啊
Professor Moriya challenged me,
教授向我挑战
and tried to damage my good reputation as a high school detective.
想让我这个高中生侦探名声受损
By doing this, he could not only get back at me,
不仅可以达到报复我的目的
but also achieve his other goal,
同时也能达到他的另一个目的
which is make it look like camouflage for the arson and the bomb incident.
就是作为连续纵火案和炸弹事件的障眼法
Plus, at that time,
还有那时
he stopped the timer in the cage
他之所以让宠物笼里的计时器暂停
because the gas lamps in the children's park
是因为儿童公园里的瓦斯灯
are the symbol he designed for the new town in Nishitamashi.
那是他设计的西多摩市新城镇的象征
So, he didn't want to destroy the lamps,
所以教授不希望它被破坏掉
which are in his favorite London style.
不想破坏他最爱的伦敦风格的瓦斯灯
Am I right?
没错吧
Kudo's deductions are really very interesting.
工藤的推理的确很有意思
But it's pity that you don't have any proof.
不过遗憾的是你的推理根本没有证据
Of course I have.
证据我当然有
It's behind that model.
就在那个模型的后面
It's the tool which the bomber used to disguise himself.
这是爆炸案疑犯的变装道具
How could it be? I put them in the safe in the study.
怎么可能 我明明把它放在书房的保险柜里
Really?
是吗
So the bomber's disguise is in the safe in your study.
原来爆炸案疑犯的变装道具在书房的保险柜里啊
What?
什么
These are my glasses.
这个其实是我的眼镜
I blackened it with a felt-tip pen.
我用水性笔把它涂黑了
As for how I made the beard and wig,
至于胡子和假发
I cut the hair from the armor in the study and taped it up.
是我把书房里盔甲上的毛剪下后用胶带粘贴成的
This was all Shinichi's idea.
这些全都是新一哥哥想的点子
Professor Moriya,
森谷教授
please come to the police station with me.
请跟我们到警署去吧
Freeze.
不准动
If you dare move, I'll detonate the bombs in the room.
谁要是敢动我就引爆房间里的炸弹
That's impossible.
不可能爆炸啦
Because there's no battery
因为那个引爆装置
in the detonation device.
里面没有电池啊
How could it be?
怎么可能
When-when did you...
你 你什么时候…
How did you know this is a detonated device?
你怎么会知道这是引爆装置呢
Because you never used a lighter.
因为叔叔你不用打火机啊
When you lit your pipe, you only used matches.
点烟斗的时候都是用那种长长的火柴
The fragrant smell which Ayumi talked about
步美说的那种香香的气味
must have been the smell of your pipe.
其实就是烟斗的气味
Arrest him.
逮捕他
Perfect. This has finally been solved.
太好了 这件事总算是解决了
Congratulations! Congratulations to us!
可喜可贺 可喜可贺
What's so happy about, Mr. Mouri?
这有什么好可喜可贺的 毛利先生
How could say that
你也太过份了吧
I was the criminal?
竟然说我是犯人
I'm sorry.
对不起
But everyone makes mistakes.
所谓人有失手马有失蹄嘛
This is not a mistake,
我看叔叔你不是失手
it's just rudeness!
根本就是失礼嘛
You are making a huge mistake if you think this is over.
如果以为事情已经结束那就大错特错了
There's another structure I want to blow up.
我想破坏的建筑物还有另外一栋呢
Is that Beika City Building?
难道是米花都市大楼
Is that building not completely symmetrical either?
莫非那里也不是完全的左右对称吗
They said that they were underfunded because of the bubble economy.
说什么泡沫经济崩溃没有足够的经费
Due to that absurd reason,
就因为这种无聊的理由
that building became the biggest failure in my life.
使它成为我这辈子最失败的作品
You people don't grasp my understanding of beauty.
你们这些人根本就不懂我的美学
There's only one minute left until 10 o'clock.
现在距离10点还有1分钟
Ran.
小兰
(Beika City Building Beika No.1 Cinema)
[米花都市大楼 米花1号电影城]
This is Mouri.
我是毛利
Ran, leave the building now!
小兰姐姐 马上离开那里
Ran, are you all right?
小兰姐姐 你没事吧
Ran!
小兰姐姐
Give it to me.
给我
What's wrong? Answer me, Ran!
怎么了 快回答我 小兰
Crap!
可恶
You asshole, what did you want with Ran?
你这混蛋 到底想把小兰怎么样
Now the explosion only sealed all the entrances and exits.
现在只是把大厅的出入口和紧急出口堵住了而已
The really interesting part is yet to come.
好戏还在后头
What?
什么
Kudo,
工藤
you must be listening to me somewhere.
你大概也在某处听我说话吧
If you don't go there quickly, your girlfriend will be blown to pieces.
不快去的话你的宝贝女朋友就要被炸成碎片了哦
I'll show you no mercy.
我绝对饶不了你
Don't get violent.
不能使用暴力
What do you want to do?
你想做什么
This is?
这是
What? Is it the blueprint of the bomb?
什么 是炸弹的设计图吗
What?
什么
I'll bring it to Shinichi!
我现在就把它拿去给新一哥哥
Wait!
等一下
I'll send in a bomb squad.
我现在就派炸弹拆除小组过去
There's no time for that!
没时间等炸弹拆除小组了
Wait,
慢着
if you meet Kudo, tell him this.
如果见到工藤 你就这样告诉他
I reserved 3 minutes specially for you.
我特别为你预留了3分钟
Please enjoy it.
请你好好地享受吧
Wait, Conan!
等一下 柯南
Shiratori, I'll leave Professor Moriya to you.
白鸟 森谷教授拜托你了
Sure.
是
Ran!
小兰
Where are you, Ran?
你在哪里 小兰
Shoot.
可恶
Mouri.
毛利老弟
Ran.
小兰
Inspector, what is the rescue team doing?
警官 救援小组到底在搞什么啊
Calm down, Mouri.
冷静点 毛利老弟
Calm down.
冷静点
Ran, wait there,
小兰 你等着
I'm coming for you!
我马上就来
We're going to be all right.
不会有事的
Someone is going to rescue us soon.
马上就会有人来救我们了
Hello.
喂
Ran?
小兰吗
Shinichi.
新一
Great, the phone is still working.
太好了 电话线路好像还没断
What the heck?
你在搞什么
Why are you always not with me at the most critical moment?
为什么最关键的时刻你总是不在呢
It's always like this.
每次都这样
Do you know what is happening to me now?
你知道我现在遇到什么事了吗
I know.
我都知道
I'm outside the emergency exit which was blocked by the rubble.
我现在就在被瓦砾堵住的紧急出口外边
It was hard to slip into the cracks in the rubble.
刚才好不容易从瓦砾的缝隙里钻了进来
But, because of the blast,
可是由于爆炸的冲击
the whole shape of the door was changed.
这扇门整个都变形了
I can't open it.
我怎么也打不开
By the way,
对了
is there anything in the hall you found suspicious, something like a briefcase or some luggage?
大厅里有没有公文包或行李箱之类的可疑物品
Something suspicious?
可疑物品
I don't know what this is.
不知道是什么
It's very heavy thing inside a big bag,
又重又大的一袋呢
with something like a digital watch on the top.
上面还有个像电子表一样的东西
Be careful, that's a bomb.
小心点 那是炸弹
A bomb?
炸弹
That evil professor,
可恶的教授
he put the biggest bomb here.
果然把最大的炸弹放在了这里
Ran, how much time do we have?
小兰 还剩多少时间
Wait.
等一下
42 minutes and 7 seconds.
还有42分7秒
There are still 42 minutes.
还有42分钟
So the bomb will explode at three minutes past midnight.
这么说来爆炸的时间是0点03分
Three?
03分
I reserved 3 minutes for you specially.
我特别为你预留了3分钟
Please do enjoy it.
请你好好地享受吧
What does the 3 minutes mean?
这3分钟是什么意思
How's it going?
怎么样
This is bad.
不行
The stairs on every floor have been buried by rubble.
每个楼层的楼梯都被瓦砾掩埋了
It'll take some time for us to get to the hall on the 5th floor where the people are trapped.
要到达群众被困的5楼大厅恐怕还要花点时间
Ran!
小兰
Only 18 minutes left.
还剩18分钟
There's not enough time.
没有时间了
In that case-
事到如今
Ran, do you have a pair of scissors with you?
小兰 你身上有没有带剪刀
There is a pair in my handbag.
我的缝纫袋里有一把小剪刀
What do you need it for?
你要剪刀做什么
I need you to use it to defuse the bomb.
我要你来拆除炸弹
Listen, do as I say.
听好 照我说的去做
Wait,
等等
I can't do something like that while listening to you on the phone!
我没办法一边听电话一边做事
I'll go to you now.
我现在就到你那边去
Wait.
等一下
Okay.
好
Looks like there's no vibration sensor on it.
看样子上面没有震动感应装置
But you still need to walk as gently as you can.
不过手脚还是要轻点
I know.
我知道了
Can you hear me, Shinichi?
你听得到吗 新一
I can hear you clearly.
听得很清楚
Now I'm ripping the bag.
那我把袋子撕破了哦
Be careful.
小心一些
What's wrong, Ran?
怎么了 小兰
Are you all right?
你没事吧
I'm fine.
我没事
OK, I'm ready.
ok 我已经准备好了
Great.
好
Move away the cover first.
先把外面的盖子拿开
You can pick it up directly.
直接拿起来就行了
Be gentle.
轻一点哦
I did it, Shinichi.
我拿开了 新一
Good job!
很好
Now, you are going to cut the lines inside.
现在开始要把里面的电线剪断
If you do it in the wrong order, we'll be dead.
如果把顺序弄错的话我们就没命了
First, cut the yellow line at the bottom.
首先剪最下面的黄色电线
I'm going to cut it.
我要剪了哦
Inspector.
警官
Will Ran...
小兰她该不会…
Calm down, Mouri.
冷静点 毛利老弟
The place where Ran is didn't explode.
爆炸的地点不是小兰那里
Don't worry.
放心吧
Your daughter will be blown to pieces in 15 minutes.
你的女儿还要过15分钟才会粉身碎骨
How dare you?!
你这家伙
Tell us!
快说
How can we stop that bomb from exploding?
到底要怎样才能阻止那个炸弹爆炸
That's a special bomb.
那是一个特别设计的炸弹
Even if she can defuse it, she has to bet on the last line.
就算能顺利拆除 也必须赌一下最后那条线
The line of destiny.
命运之线啊
There was an explosion in Beika City Building just now...
目前在米花都市大楼发生了爆炸事件…
I cut it.
剪断了
Good.
很好
So it's not too late.
这样看来应该还来得及
Now you only need to cut the black line.
现在只要把剩下的黑线剪断计时器就会停了
The black one, right?
黑色的是吗
Shi-Shinichi.
新 新一
I already cut the black line.
我已经把黑色的那条剪断了
But the timer didn't stop.
可是计时器没有停啊
Also, there are still two lines left.
而且电线还剩下两条
A red one and a blue one.
一条红的 一条蓝的
What?
你说什么
We have opened the tunnel to the fourth floor.
往4楼的通道终于被打通了
Make it as quick as you can.
尽量快一点
The explosion will take place in 4 minutes.
距离爆炸只剩下4分钟时间了
Mr. Mouri.
毛利先生
Ran, Ran, I'm coming for you!
小兰 小兰 我马上就来了
Where are you going, Mr. Mouri?
你要去哪里 毛利先生
Let go of me.
放开我
Ran, I have to save Ran!
小兰 我要去救小兰
You can't go. The rescue team will get her out.
不能去 救援人员正在处理
Ran!
小兰
Is this the tragedy of fatherly love?
这就是悲哀的父女之爱吗
Architecture doesn't need love,
建筑是不需要爱的
and neither does one's life.
人生也是
So Professor Moriya didn't draw the two lines on the paper
难道森谷教授为了引我上当
in order to leave me stumped here?
故意没在这张设计图上画那两条线吗
What should I do?
怎么办
Should I cut both of the lines?
两条都要剪断吗
Idiot!
笨蛋
One of them is the detonating cord!
其中一条是真正的引爆线
If you cut it, we'll be blown to pieces!
一剪掉我们就会粉身碎骨
It-it can'be!
怎 怎么会
Shoot!
可恶
Which one is it?
哪一条呢
The red one or the blue one?
红色还是蓝色
Which line should we cut?
到底该剪哪条才好
It's 12 o'clock.
12点了
We only have 3 minutes left.
还剩下3分钟
Damn it.
可恶
Which one?
哪一条
Which one is it?
到底是哪一条
Shinichi.
新一
Happy Birthday.
生日快乐
I said it because
因为
I might never have the chance to say it to you in person.
以后可能没机会对你说这句话了
Ran.
小兰
Cut it.
剪吧
Cut the one you like.
剪你喜欢的那一条吧
What if I get it wrong?
可是 要是剪错的话怎么办
It doesn't matter.
剪错就剪错吧
It will explode when time is up anyway.
反正时间到了还是会爆炸
Since then, just choose the color you like.
既然这样就剪你喜欢的颜色好了
B-but-
可 可是
Don't worry.
不用担心
I'll be here with you
直到你剪断为止
when you cut it.
我都会一直在这里陪你
I'll die with you.
我会陪你一起死
Shinichi.
新一
Shinichi, which color do you prefer, red or blue?
新一你喜欢红色还是蓝色
I think it's red.
那就红色吧
By the way, look at this,
对了 你们看这个
Shinichi's lucky color for May is the same as mine, which is red.
我和新一五月份的幸运色都是红色
That's why I decided to watch that movie.
所以我才决定要去看这部片子的
Ran, Ran, are you alright?
小兰 小兰 你没事吧
Damn it, she can't hear me now.
可恶 听不到了吗
That's right, I can use my cell phone.
对了 用手机
It's gone.
不见了
Crap, did I drop it?
糟糕 是刚才弄丢了吗
We found a boy here.
在这里找到一个少年
It's fine, little boy.
已经没事了 小弟弟
Let's go now.
我们快走吧
W-Wait a moment.
等 等一下
There's something stuck in here.
还有人被困在这里面
Fine, wait here for a second.
那好 你等一下
I can't bust it open. Get the drill ready.
撞不开 准备钻岩工具
Yes.
是
Today is my anniversary.
今天是我的结婚纪念日
It looks like I can't enjoy it.
看来没办法好好过了
I reserved 3 minutes for you specially.
我特别为你预留了3分钟
Please do enjoy it.
请你好好地享受吧
I see.
原来如此
So he wants me to enjoy the three minutes of my birthday.
原来他是要我好好享受这3分钟过生日的滋味
Wait.
等一下
I remember at that time.
我记得那个时候
You must be looking forward to it.
那真是令人期待
I guess you have bought the gift already.
你一定把礼物也买好了吧
No, I want to buy it on Saturday.
没有 我想星期六再买
Because he likes red like I do.
因为他和我一样很喜欢红色
Also, our lucky color for May is red.
而且我们五月份的幸运色也都是红色
The lucky color.
幸运色
Shoot.
糟了
Let's go, boy.
快走吧 小弟弟
- Little boy. - Ran!
小弟弟 -小兰
Don't cut the red line!
不能剪红色
Cut the blue one!
剪蓝色那条
You can't cut the red one!
不能剪红色那条
Ran!
小兰
What's wrong?
怎么了
Answer my question.
快回答我
Ran!
小兰
Goodbye.
再见了
Shinichi!
新一
Ran!
小兰
How-how's that possible?
怎 怎么可能
I'm so glad that Ran was safe, Mouri.
小兰能够平安无事真是太好了 毛利老弟
Yes.
是
Thank you very much.
真是谢谢你
Hello, may I speak to you?
你好 请说句话好吗
As the famous detective, what's your opinion about...
身为名侦探的你对这次…
To be honest, this time the criminal tried to
老实说这次的炸弹事件
damage my good reputation as a famous detective.
犯人是想破坏我这个名侦探的声誉
So he set Ran, my daughter, in this dangerous situation.
才会设计让我女儿小兰掉进他的陷阱里
Conan!
柯南
Did you come here because you were worried about me?
你也是因为担心我而来的吗
Yeah.
对啊
What's with this bandage?
这个绷带是怎么回事
I tripped over myself just now.
刚才不小心跌倒了
You have to be careful.
以后要小心点才行哦
Conan, did you see Shinichi?
柯南 你有没有看到新一啊
It's so weird. He was here just now.
奇怪 他刚才明明还在这里
I already bought a gift for him.
人家还买了礼物要送给他的
By the way, Shinichi seemed very surprised
对了 新一哥哥刚才还一直觉得不可思议呢
because he thought you would cut the red line.
他以为小兰姐姐一定会剪掉红色电线
He didn't understand why you cut the blue one.
不明白为什么你却剪掉了蓝色的
Because I don't want to cut it off,
因为我不想把它给剪断嘛
the red line.
那条红色的线
Maybe that's the red line which connects Shinichi and me together!
说不定就是系住我和新一的红线啊
The red line's not there!
没有啊 红线
Right, I'm Conan now.
我现在是柯南
There's no way it'd be there.
不可能有吧